Please identify the accused.
Dr. William Chester Minor...
Captain Surgeon in the US Army,
retired.
Dr. Minor has come to our shores
seeking sanctuary.
In his home country of the
United States, he was pursued...
relentlessly by a man pledged
to torture and kill him.
On that fateful night...
of the 17th of February, the
defendant woke with a start...
he knew right away that he had
been hunted down and found...
that his pursuer, one Declan
Reilly was indeed, in his rooms.
Dr. Minor reached for his
service revolver and gave chase.
Fenian!
In the
streets, he found a man running.
Help! Help!
Help!
Eliza, open the door! Eliza!
Eliza!
In the confusion of night...
he failed to discern the
difference...
between his assailant and the
innocent George Merrett.
Eliza.
Stop there!
This is not the Fenian!
No!
This is not the Fenian?
I'm sorry! Sorry!
No!
My Lord, Dr. Minor shot the
wrong man.
So... he didn't mean it.
My Lord, perhaps the court
should simply release...
the good doctor with an
apology...
for the misunderstanding that
has occurred.
Your Honor!?
Declan... Declan Reilly
is his name!
He has a brand on the left side
of his face, he comes at night!
He comes with others, they haunt
me, they come into my rooms!
I do not believe you, sir.
This court does not believe you.
Quiet, please! Quiet in court!
Quiet, please! Quiet!
Quiet, quiet!
We, the members of her Majesty's
jury...
find Dr. William Chester Minor
not guilty...
of the willful murder
of George Merrett...
Quiet! Quiet!
...on the grounds of insanity.
I am not insane, sir.
Quiet, please!
William Chester Minor, it is
hereby this court's ruling...
that you shall be detained
in safe custody...
at Broadmoor Asylum for the
Criminally Insane...
until Her Majesty's pleasure
be known.
Quiet, please!
Move, move!
Bloody bollocks hell!
Hey! Any more of that
and you're off!
Harold!
I must get back in, father.
In a tick, boy. Take a few
breaths.
Mind the long run down the
flank.
If you see the brute coming,
stay downpitch...
and don't let him pull you in,
all right?
And try for the clean catch.
Yes, sir. The game, sir.
Harold, about your use
of words...
Yes, sir.
- Good. In you go, boy, go on.
- Yes, sir!
I had a word with him.
Yes, I saw.
In the paper, a dreadful story,
a shooting in Lambeth...
by an American, an army
officer...
and that poor woman left behind
with six children.
That I saw.
I don't know what I would do,
James...
if you were taken like that.
Yes! That's it, that's it!
Yes! Yes!
Yes, yes! How's that, you
ensanguined mule?
- That's it, you're off!
- What's wrong with ensanguined?
- Get off!
- Harold! Harold!
I wish to state that I possess
a general lexical...
and structural knowledge of the
languages...
and literature of the Aryan
and Syro-Arabic classes.
I have recently submitted my
paper on the declension...
of German verbs to the
Philological Society.
Mr. Murray, I understand that...
you do not possess
a university degree.
No, sir, no degree.
I am an autodidact, self-taught.
I am aware of the word.
Schooling?
Left at 14 to earn a living.
Honestly, Freddie, it's a bit
much.
A bit much, yes.
Of course, we, the august
delegates...
of the Oxford University
Press...
have been attempting to make
this dictionary...
for the last 20 years.
And despite the greatest efforts
of a whole army of academics...
myself included, we are
precisely nowhere.
Forgive me that is incorrect.
We are, in fact, going
backwards.
The language is developing
faster than our progress.
This great tongue of ours, which
reaches out across the world...
has drawn its guns, sharpened
its bayonets...
and declared that it will not
be tamed.
And we, with our debates ad
nauseam about the scope...
the mode, the purpose of these
words have all...
but thrown ourselves down
in supplication before it...
bathed in abject defeat.
At this moment, the endeavor
is dead.
Is that too much, Max?
Gentlemen, I'm afraid nothing...
short of a panacea is called
for.
I submit that the extraordinary,
the unconventional...
Mr. Murray is the solution
and our salvation.
Your account, though a bit
dramatic, is true, Freddie.
But we need something more than
impassioned advocacy.
Qualifications come to mind.
Perhaps a Bachelor's Degree.
Qualifications, yes.
Well, I am fluent in Latin and
Greek, of course.
Beyond those, I have an intimate
knowledge...
of the Romance tongues, Italian,
French, Spanish...
Catalan and to a lesser degree
Portuguese, Vaudois...
Provencal and other dialects.
In the Teutonic branch, I am
familiar with German, Dutch...
Danish and Flemish.
I have specialized in
Anglo-Saxon and Moeso-Gothic...
and have prepared works
for publication...
in both of these languages.
I also have a useful knowledge
of Russian.
I have sufficient knowledge of
Hebrew and Syriac to read...
at sight the Old Testament and
the Peshito...
to a lesser degree, Aramaic,
Arabic, Coptic...
and Phoenician to the point
where it was left by Genesius.
Forgive me rattling on.
I'm sure you have questions.
Mr. Murray, a word comes
to mind... clever.
Can you define it and tell us
its history?
I'll make a fist of it, on the
hoof, as it were.
Clever: adjective. Meaning -
adroit, nimble, dextrous.
Probably from the Low German,
Klover.
Or perhaps the Middle Dutch,
Klever...
with a "k", meaning sprightly
or smart.
Mr. Murray is also a master
of the Scottish clog dance.
Forgive me for keeping
it from you...
I scarcely believed in the
chance myself.
It's all mine, Ada, the entire
language.
I've never known how to resist
it, your exuberance...
but it's so sudden.
And to abandon all this, the
school, the constancy.
Is it truly what you wish
for all of us?
Ada, I'm an untutored linen
draper's boy from Teviotdale...
now, suddenly, with a real crack
at it.
My entire life has been in
preparation for this.
The call has finally come.
Whatever I've done,
I've done with you.
I've never been able to
without you.
Once again, lend yourself to me?
If I am to fashion a book,
I'll need a spine.
Father!
Elsie, children.
Are we going somewhere?
To Oxford, your father
is the editor...
of the New English Dictionary
on Historical Principles.
What is that?
It's a very big book with a lot
of words in it.
All the words of the English
language.
Like Doctor Johnson's
Dictionary?
Yes, but his book comprised of
only a mere handful of words.
I am charged with identifying
and defining every last word!
Will "happy" be in there,
Father?
Aye, "happy" will be there,
Elsie.
My dictionary will need as many
volumes as these...
to house the entire language.
Will "sad"?
"Sad" will be there, yes, aye.
What about "big", will "big"
be in there?
Yeah, aye, and "small" too.
There isn't a word you can
think of that...
will not be in this very
big book.
- Father?
- Yes, Oswyn.
Will "Oswyn" be in there?
Uh... probably...
Never play with books,
all right? That's wrong.
BRAYN Wednesday, April
17, 1872. Inmate number 742.
742, admittance.
BRAYN
Minor, William Chester...
American, 48 years old...
surgeon, a captain in the
United States Army.
No known religion, classified
a danger to others.
Assigned to Block Two.
The prisoner is in a rage,
spitting dozens of times...
by his own account trying not
to swallow poison-coated...
cold, iron bars that have been
pressed against his teeth.
In you go.
BRAYN March 17th...
three days now the prisoner
has gone without sleep.
Constantly leaping from his bed
to search...
underneath it in sheer terror.
Repeatedly claiming to look for
those coming for him at night.
Doctor Richard Brayn, alienist
superintendent...
Broadmoor Asylum.
There it was, staring me
in the face...
the Home Secretary wouldn't be
bamboozled into accepting.
Can you believe it?
Like Orthrus, a two-headed dog
of a line.
Written... in the Athenaeum...
in a single sentence!
Your book, Mr. Murray, will need
to establish strict rules...
banning such offenses.
Beyond which it should fix all
spellings...
lay down proper
pronunciations...
and firm up correctness
of speech.
We've been here before, Max.
What of all the bamboozles, the
wouldn'ts, the shouldn'ts...
and the couldn'ts to come
in the future?
The tongue is at its purest
peak.
Sufficiently refined that it can
henceforward only deteriorate.
It is up to us to fix it once
and for all.
Alterations to it can then be
permitted or not.
You, Max? Me? No.
All words are valid in the
language.
Ancient or new, obsolete or
robust...
foreign-born or home-grown.
The book must inventory every
word, every nuance...
every twist of etymology and
every possible illustrated...
citation from every English
author.
All of it or nothing at all.
That would mean reading
everything.
Quoting everything that showed
anything to do...
with the history of the words
that are to be cited.
The task is gigantic,
monumental.
And impossible.
There is a way.
A task that might take one man
a hundred lifetimes...
could take a hundred men
just one.
Volunteers. We have tried it
before, James, and failed.
I'm afraid there aren't enough
academics in the land.
How many did you enlist?
Eighty, perhaps ninety.
With a thousand, you could
accomplish it...
in just a few years.
Where do you propose finding
a thousand men?
Everywhere English is celebrated
and spoken.
In every book shop, school,
workplace or home.
Do you mean ordinary people,
amateurs?
English speaking ones, aye.
We will ask them to read...
in search of the words that we
want, and get them to write...
the word on a slip of paper,
along with a quotation...
that they have found
illustrating the very word.
And then? Post the slip tass.
An entire army covering the
breadth of the Empire...
and beyond, drawing a sweep
net...
over the whole of English
literature...
listing the entirety of their
own language.
A dictionary by democracy.
Still edited by us, learned men.
And with this system,
Mr. Murray...
how long do you estimate
to finishing your task?
Five years, seven at most.
All words... and their complete
histories?
Every last one.
Dear England...
We are about to embark on the
greatest adventure...
our language has ever known.
Let us begin at aardvark...
and never stop 'til we reach
Zymurgy.
Zymurgy?
I would wager that that is the
last word in the language.
Surely there is nothing
after Z-Y.
Meaning?
There's a cloying
eagerness to him.
Yes.
And that grating Scottish
lilt...
why do you suppose he doesn't
try to conceal it...
for the sake of our eardrums.
His ideas are quite radical,
just what we need.
You don't think he's a
follower...
of that awful German-born
pamphleteer, do you?
No, no, no, my dear.
This man is positively baying to
be part of this little world...
of ours, already quite seduced,
I would say.
I'm sorry, Ada.
What for?
For this disruption,
for breaking up the home...
for dragging you here.
No doubts, James, no jitters.
I need this promise from you.
Now that it's started,
let's see it through...
steadfast and resolved.
MURRAY An appeal to
the English-reading public...
of Great Britain, America
and the British colonies...
to read books and make extracts
for a new dictionary...
worthy of the English language.
We live today knowing the
origins of the Earth...
of man and all the animals.
We know how hot boiling water
is, how long a yard.
Our ships' masters know the
precise measurements...
of latitude and longitude.
Yet we have neither chart nor
compass to guide us...
through the wide sea of words.
The time has come to accord
this great language of ours...
the same dignity and respect as
the other standards...
defined by science. Fly your
words to Oxford.
Let us be connected, all of us
in this great endeavour...
through the marvelous maze
of our inter-netted post.
What are you doing, Father?
Mr. Bradley and I are putting
a big hole in the ground.
- But what for?
- For a scriptorium.
That's a room like in medieval
monasteries...
where monastic scribes used
to copy manuscripts.
Look, look at that, look what
I found! Treasure!
Will you clean that for me?
Yes, Father.
Aye.
MURRAY
It is a long run...
but we can bear the language
aloft.
Mr. Bradley.
MURRAY
With you, our volunteers...
as rungs in the ladder...
we may elevate English even
unto the gates of heaven.
- Come on.
- Get off me!
Easy.
Get him off of me! Who did
that to me?
Stand clear! Get out of the way!
Go on, take me!
Get out of the way, get back!
Get back, now, now, move, move!
Look at me, look at me!
Son, son, listen to me,
listen to me.
We're gonna lift the gate
just a bit...
let's see if you can pull
your leg through.
I-I don't know, sir.
We've gotta do it, son,
we gotta do it.
Will you let us try?
Hey, hey?
Good boy, good boy...
after three, one, two...
Out of my way! Out of my way!
How far is the nearest
blacksmith?
Crowthorne.
The nearest surgeon?
Crowthorne Village, it's half
an hour, there and back.
I want a sharp knife and a saw.
Get it up!
Agh!
In a half hour's time, this man
will have bled to death.
- Coleman.
- Yes, sir.
Get a sharp knife and a saw...
quickly!
Now you listen to me, doctor,
I know who you are...
and how you got in here...
and believe me when I say
that none of your wealth...
will do you any good if you
try anything.
Your saw.
You wrap the wound in boiled
rags.
Keep the belt tight and get him
to a surgeon.
Your ligation held,
hemorrhaging was low...
his condition is delicate,
but he is alive.
We are all extremely grateful
to you, Dr. Minor.
Was the wound swabbed, dressed
in phenol?
Luckily, our local surgeon is
well versed...
in Lister's latest antisepsis
and asepsis methods...
as I see are you.
Rush's Tranquilizer.
Dr. Rush, he was an American
Army surgeon for a time...
as well, I believe.
Dr. Rush believed that if the
patient could be rendered...
entirely immobile during the
convulsions of mania...
then madness itself would be
countered.
Barbaric in its simplicity.
It's a relic, really, from the
dark days of my profession...
but it still has its uses when
combined with modern techniques.
You think I'm insane.
Are we not all, to some extent?
You do experience yourself as
being under threat, do you not?
A man... is coming for me.
From my confinement, I will not
see him come.
So if you will permit me,
I would ask your vigilance.
And that you have your men
alert me.
He is easily identifiable.
He has a brand mark on the left
side of his face.
Dr. Minor, rest assured we will
do everything...
in our power to ensure your
safety.
Is there anything else I can
help you with?
I have a pension from the United
States Army.
I wish that the greater portion
of it...
be given to Mrs. Merrett
in support of her children.
Well, I'm sure that can be
arranged.
Sir? I'd like to take care
of that personally.
There you are, Dr. Minor.
You have our very best man
on the case.
There are children
sleeping here.
Only a letter to deliver, ma'am.
Bit late for the post,
ain't it?
You lot are terrible liars.
I'm not from the papers, or the
police, I'm not.
Not here to bother you at all.
I needed to make sure you got
it right personal.
I'll just slide it under the
door.
I'm not from the papers.
Who are you, then?
I'm Muncie, ma'am, I'm hoping
to help.
Is this from you?
No, ma'am, the letter will
explain.
Who's it from?
She wouldn't consider it.
Thank you, Mr. Muncie.
Look again, we must have it.
I have looked and we do not...
I have quotes for it in the
14th, the 15th...
the 16th and the 19th, but not
in the 17th and 18th centuries.
How is that possible?
How can Ruskin write "The
sculpture is approved...
"and set off by the color"
in 1849?
How can I, now use it everyday,
if you are telling me...
that it vanished in the 17th
Century.
Where did it go for 200 years?
I am not saying that it
vanished, sir.
I am simply saying that we do
not have proof.
Look again, Charles.
And where exactly would you like
me to look, sir...
in the birthday cards, perhaps
or the medicinal instructions...
or the How-to manuals...
or perhaps the Guy Fawkes
day messages?
And we're only just dealing
with "A" here.
What of B, C, D, E, F,
G, H, I, J, K?
It's bloody hopeless, sir!
Mr. Hall! Please try to maintain
a semblance of decorum.
Henry, what exactly is the
problem here?
It's "Approve", sir. There is a
missing link.
To say nothing of "Art".
We're missing "Approve" in the
17th and 18th centuries.
We can't find a single trace
of it.
Look at Paradise Lost.
The language took a crucial turn
with Milton.
He was somewhat of a purist...
re-affirming the meaning of his
English.
The key would be in there.
Try that.
Perhaps we can skip the 17th
century, sir.
We have its birth in 1380 with
John Wyclif.
"Christ confirmed his law and
with his death approved it."
And we have Ruskin here
in this century.
Mr. Bradley, we must have every
step.
This is not about the centuries.
This is about recording the
evolution of meaning.
Go to Milton, it's right here.
Yes, sir.
Mr. Bradley.
Charles.
Accepted.
Razor! Bring me my razor!
Sir Richard! Calm down!
The razor, bring me my razor!
Lads, bloody well hurry up!
Bring it, bring me the razor!
- Bring me the razor!
- Come on, hurry up!
Father! Father! Father! Father!
Father! Father! Father!
This man, Declan
Reilly, is a deserter.
Mark him for what he is.
Agh!
Zinc... I'll need sheets
of zinc...
he must have come from below.
And water, in a bowl, by the
threshold.
This, the demon will not pass.
What's on the other side,
doctor?
The night, he wants to take me
there.
With his blind eyes, he can only
see me in the dark.
How would you feel if we
brightened the light?
As treatment?
I don't need treatment!
Not as treatment! As an
experiment!
I need to see him come so I can
defend myself!
An experiment in
self-protection...
we embark on together, doctor,
yes?
Let me take a look at these.
Superficial lacerations,
multiple to the face.
How would you feel, doctor...
if we were to introduce some
of the comforts of home?
Orthognathous jaw, facial angle,
80 degrees...
maybe some clothing.
Amativeness, 8 incline...
Philoprogenitiveness, 4 decline.
How would that be?
My own wardrobe as protection?
As protection, precisely.
Adhesiveness, 3 constant.
Combativeness, 6 incline.
Secretiveness, 8.
Hope, 4, constant.
Yes, the simple things that we
can fit into your surroundings.
It also happens that the
adjoining cell...
has become available, you could
stretch your legs.
I could have easels with paints.
Certainly. Wonder, Ideality,
Wit, Form. All 8, decline.
Eventuality undetermined. Do you
have any other requests, doctor?
My books. May I have my books?
By all means, anything else?
My gun.
Perhaps we'll give that one
a miss.
Thank you, doctor.
Please, don't thank me.
It has been a long time since
anyone has...
My dear friend, no thanks, no
thanks...
a new beginning.
Yes, a new beginning, yes.
BRAYN How can a man of
such high breeding...
have regressed through disease
so far back to animality?
Doctor?
Mr. Muncie?
We wanted to give you this, sir,
the lads all chipped in.
And what have we here?
It's a book, sir. We're all
grateful to you.
Yes, it is. Thank you,
Mr. Muncie.
For saving a young guard's life,
sir.
I will read it avidly and I will
treasure it forever!
You thank your men on my behalf!
Merry Christmas, sir.
Merry Christmas, you, too, yes.
Ham, Mr. Muncie!
Sir?
I find that a good, warm ham is
often better...
for fighting the cold than any
number of blankets...
or coals in the fire, especially
at this time of year.
Did he like the book, sir?
- The book?
- Yeah.
- I don't know.
- Well, has he read it?
- Well, he opened the wrapping.
- Yes, sir.
- And then he opened the book.
- Yes.
And then he threw it out
the window.
He what?
Yeah, he said a demon vaporized
off the page...
and went up his nostrils.
His nostrils?
He's in there now trying to pull
out his nose hairs.
MURRAY To chart the life
of each word, we must start...
with a record of its birth,
when it was first written down.
From there, words come down to
us through the ages...
twisting and turning, weaving
their way.
Their meanings slipping and
slivering, offishlike, adding..
and shedding subtleties of
nuance to and from themselves.
But they leave tracks...
in the great expanse of the
literature...
of the English language.
MURRAY We will chase
them, hunt them...
and ferret them out, all
of them, every single word...
from all the centuries
of writing...
and we will do so by reading
every single book.
Can it be done?
You crazy, beautiful bastard!
Guard! Guard!
Ink, I'll need ink.
Yes, sir, I understand, sir.
- Paper.
- Yes, sir.
- Lots and lots of it.
- I'll see what I can do, doctor.
And Coleman...
Yes, sir?
Would you be so kind as to
dispose of this for me?
What is it, sir?
You can't see?
Yes... of course, I can, sir...
Yes, nasal hair, mind the
demonic vapors...
make sure to wash your hands...
and I'll make sure to fish out
some more later.
- Thank you, sir.
- Thank you, Coleman.
I'm too cold. I'm gonna get
myself home.
We'll warm each other up,
come on.
- I'm too cold.
- Oh, you got a smile.
- I can't, it's too cold!
- Come on!
No!
No, no, you promised me!
You promised me!
Get off, I don't owe you
nothing!
What am I meant to feed my
little ones with, eh?
I don't know, ask their father.
How are them matches coming, eh?
Mum, you alright?
Yeah, yeah, I just needed
a moment.
Please, can I help you?
It'll be alright.
Good evening, I was
wondering, is your mum around?
We'll get those matches done
by night's end.
It's a man at the door.
Tell him it's Christmas and
he'll go away.
Could you just give her
this for me...
and tell your mother Happy
Christmas from Mr. Muncie?
Goodnight, girls.
Mum?
It's a ham in one, the other,
he didn't say.
He said tell your mum
Happy Christmas.
Happy Christmas from Mr. Muncie.
It's alright then, isn't it,
Mum?
Sir, stop, sir, please!
Yes, dear?
Is that supposed to be me?
Yeah.
Good night, then, Mrs. Merrett.
Good night... and thank you.
Forgive me for saying, ma'am...
but it doesn't have to be
this way.
The children... they don't need
to go hungry.
There is one waiting to feed
them.
Take me to him.
Let me look him in the eye,
see if I can stomach him.
I went to a banquet
and I ate apples...
bananas, and cranberries.
I went to the banquet and I ate
apples...
bananas, cranberries, and...
dog.
That can't be, you can't eat
Yes, I can.
No, you can't.
Mum! Mother! Mum?
Merry Christmas all!
Hey! We're taking fire,
Mr. Bradley!
Pounce on them!
Ah, you wee...!
Well, you deserved it.
Faster!
Do you remember our first
Christmas at the school?
Harold was no more than 8 or 9
months old.
Such a fat, little baby. Do you
remember how he used to cry?
Oh, god.
One night, he was screaming so
hard...
I don't know how his little body
could do it.
Every ounce of him shrieking.
Nothing I tried would calm him.
I was frightened, then you
came home.
You lifted him up into your
arms...
you held him to your chest,
and he stopped.
He was so exhausted he fell
asleep instantly.
It's always been that way,
with all of them.
You had something I didn't.
So I taught myself to be what
you were not.
Strict, fixed, changeless.
A queen and a clown, together
a perfect whole.
What if it changed?
What if you're not there
to be the clown?
I know I've been less than
present lately...
but change will come,
and for the better.
I wish I had your certainty.
Want to put the fire out when
you come to bed?
Ah, I thought you might be here,
sir.
I have a few hours before my
little ones wake...
for Christmas morning.
I thought I might take another
look at Approve.
That'll make it two of us.
William? Dr. Minor?
I have a proposal for you.
There's been a request
for a meeting.
Tristram Shandy, a gift from Mr.
Muncie and his men...
but much more.
This is very delicate.
I'll need books, far more
volumes...
than I have within my own reach.
William, I think this could be
very important for us.
Oxford University has undertaken
an inventory...
of the entire English language,
and they've asked for help.
Are you listening to me?
I'll be all right... with work,
with this work.
I'll be all right, but I need
books...
I only need books.
Make me a list of all the titles
that you require.
If I have them, I'll get them
sent to you.
Thank you, doctor.
William...
When does she want to come?
Mrs. Merrett.
- Where is he?
- It should only be a moment.
I just wanted to make sure that
everyone was breathing.
There's a real generosity
in your visit today...
Mrs. Merrett... a true courage.
Courage, doctor, is not
why I came.
Is it... is it possible
they wait?
The letter.
Yes.
All right.
How can...
We'll take care of everything,
sir.
- Thank you, doctor.
- Thank you, Mrs. Merrett.
It doesn't make it right.
What would you care to send her?
Everything.
MURRAY Few of the
earliest books have been read.
It is in the 17th and 18th
Centuries above all...
that help is urgently needed,
for nearly the whole...
of those centuries have still
to be gone through.
You may concentrate on the
rare, also late...
old-fashioned new and peculiar,
but avoid not the quotidian...
for every word in action
becomes beautiful...
in the light of its own
meaning.
Mr. Muncie! Mr. Muncie!
Sorry to have woken you, I need
your help with a post.
Yes, well, is it night?
Such a lot of it, need
envelopes, tons...
lots and lots of envelopes
and a large bag.
Yes, sir.
And a carpenter, can you bring
a carpenter by...
in the morning, of course?
Good morning, sir.
Not so good I'm afraid, Henry.
It's Art, none of it is working.
Are you sure, sir? I checked it
myself last night.
The construct is off. It has
lost all sense of coherence.
And it's missing countless
variations of meaning.
We'll have to start it anew.
But, sir, it will take weeks
just to reset the definitions.
Mr. Gell has asked for me at the
Press office this morning.
I would very much like to see
Art torn apart...
and restarted when I return, eh?
Very well, sir.
Thank you, Henry.
Your book, Mr. Murray, is
going to be an unassailable...
contribution to English
scholarship.
It will make you famous,
when it is finished.
Look around, Mr. Murray.
Empire, one quarter of the land
and peoples of this earth.
The largest trading dominion
ever known.
If one wishes to participate,
one bows down to Her Majesty...
and one speaks her tongue,
English.
Forgive me, Mr. Gell...
remind me why I am being kept
from my work this morning.
I was brought onto the press...
to modernize the commerce of
academia, to sell.
And do you know what the first
hotcake I found was?
The King James Bible...
it has sold everywhere, in every
backwater and morass...
where an Englishman is doing
God's work in a frock.
We have operations on every
continent.
Depots in Edinburgh, Toronto,
Melbourne and Calcutta.
All printing, binding,
dispatching all advertising...
and all, now, ready for the next
good book.
All waiting... for you.
What is this?
Your work is taking too long.
Our expectations constantly
revised...
and not a single page to show
for it.
The delegates have unanimously
agreed that I take charge...
of keeping the project to time.
To that effect, you have in your
hands a set of suggestions...
on how to curb the scope
of the work.
What we need is more rigorous
selection...
survival only of the fittest
words.
I'm tired. My team, we are all
beyond tired.
For months now, my pleas for
help have fallen on deaf ears.
You have refused to pay...
for even for a single additional
assistant.
I began this intending to create
something unprecedented.
To order the world of words...
making them universally
accessible and useful.
I swore that I would bend at
nothing to make it happen.
And as of now, this very moment,
my resolve is greater than ever.
You are on the verge of all out
cancellation.
These rules are designed to help
keep the work going.
You may not like them, Mr.
Murray...
but what other way is there?
My way, Mr. Gell.
Mr. Murray, we are watching
with a concerned eye.
Watch, then, and be amazed.
Lord in Heaven help me.
I am lost.
Sir! Sir! Sir?
What?
It's a miracle, it's impossible.
Calm down, man, spit it out.
- Approve, sir, it's complete.
- Complete?
You were right, sir.
"Others who approve not to
transgress by thy example"...
Milton, Paradise Lost.
You found it.
No, not us, sir. You better read
this.
It is with a great sense
of privilege...
that I offer myself up
as a volunteer.
Please, sir, read on.
MINOR Enclosed please
find one-thousand word slips...
with corresponding
quotations...
from the height and depth
of literature.
I have derived a key, a type
of dictionary...
within a dictionary, that
allows the amassing of words...
with addended quotations.
My request is simple.
To make your burden light.
Write to me, tell me what
specific words at present...
shimmer and fade at your grasp.
Let useful others troll the
oceans...
with their nets cast wide.
I shall throw my line and pluck
the very quotes...
that evade you when you call
upon me to do so.
Very truly yours, W.C. Minor,
Crowthorne, Berkshire.
Look, it's all there.
He's given us Approve in the
17th and 18th centuries.
And Art?
Not that one, but so much else.
All in the "A" s, all words
we're working on...
and at first glance all
of it usable.
God has sent us a savior.
Now all we have to do is try to
keep up with him.
Thank you, Mr. Hall.
Let's have a good look
at these slips.
Sort these now.
MURRAY You cannot fathom
the impact of both...
your offer and your timing.
I am your grateful recipient.
Let paper and ink be our flesh
and blood...
until we are privileged
to meet.
That's right.
MURRAY Enclosed are a
list of words that...
at present... are eluding us.
The word Art is proving
particularly troublesome.
MINOR Enclosed you will
find the quotations...
that you have requested.
In pondering "Art", I am
reminded of the words...
of a great man of our time
who said...
all great and beautiful work
has come of first gazing...
without shrinking into the
darkness.
May I, sir?
Aye.
Ah.
MINOR I have been much
acquainted with that darkness.
Thank you for letting me lend
my light to yours.
Together we shall shrink the
darkness...
until there is only light.
Yours, W.C. Minor. Crowthorne,
Berkshire.
Ah, here it is... heh-heh, eh.
Now we'll put your name on it,
too.
Mr. Bradley, can I have another
fascicle, please?
I know of another who's joy in
seeing it would be immeasurable.
Yes, ma'am.
Is Mr. Muncie working?
He is.
Could you please tell him Mrs.
Merrett is here to see him?
I will indeed, ma'am.
Hello, ma'am.
Mr. Muncie.
So pleased you've
returned, Mrs. Merrett.
Come on in then, ma'am.
It's... very interesting.
Come in, doctor.
Mrs. Merrett has brought you
a book.
Yes... from Maggs, the book
shop.
I was told you like to read.
Thank you.
Would you care to take a walk
on the grounds, madam?
It is a beautiful spring day.
Did you read it?
Great Expectations, the book you
brought me? Is it a favorite?
No, no, the shop suggested it.
Ah.
I came to say... thank you.
The children, they're not going
hungry no more.
They've got warm clothes now,
even for next year, but...
It's never too late with
children.
Their whole lives are tomorrows.
But I can't go on taking your
money. It's... it's not right.
- Please, Mrs. Merrett.
- It's blood money.
I know, but it's my blood, too.
My life belongs to you.
I made it so on that night.
I took a life and by dreadful
bargain...
I've placed another in your
hands.
By right, all that I have
is yours.
I don't know what to think.
I don't know why I came.
Mrs. Merrett, please!
Well, let me know if she
comes back.
Let's have a look at those
chains.
Thank you.
Can I help you, sir?
Yes, I'm here to see the
superintendent.
Are you expected?
No, I came on impulse.
I'm James Murray, I am a friend
of Dr. Minor's...
yet only through the post.
Dr. Minor, the superintendent.
Ah, ah, I came to bring him this
fruit of our labor.
I know who you are, sir.
I posted all the letters for
him. I licked the stamps myself.
Oh, thank you, for your mother
tongue.
Yeah, I'll see what I can do.
- So this is the good doctor?
- Mr. Murray, sir.
Dr. Minor, I'm proud to make
your acquaintance, sir.
I cannot believe my eyes.
Nor I, nor this surprise.
How did you gain entrance?
I came on the off chance and to
bring you this.
Our gathering, so far.
Meek, but poised to inherit
the earth.
I thank you. You deserve
to be proud.
Dumbfounded.
You've been a bulwark for us,
doctor.
I'm happy to be of assistance...
though I am merely worker to the
queen. The alveary is yours.
Ah, you sent the quote for
alveary? From...
Baret, 1580.
Of course, the early
dictionaries of English...
Latin, French and Greek,
but of course, you know that.
Of course, I don't.
I do know the poets. You, in
your letters, know the scribe.
Now my task is to de-scribe.
Alveary, such a lovely buzz
to it.
How about cosh, or fettle?
Fine. Louche.
I remember that from childhood.
It always seemed undressed.
Commotrix, I adore that one...
sounds as though it wants
trouble.
Troublesome indeed, and
difficult to find.
Gyre.
A revolution, a whirl.
Decussated.
Formed by crossing lines, an X,
an intersection.
Perhaps you should be writing
definitions and I...
well, I'd be useless tending
to your patients.
So let's leave it as it is.
We've only just started.
Partners, word for word.
An American and a Scot?
How does an American come to eye
these gates?
A story for another day.
Let's continue the comparison.
One Oxford, one Yale.
Both graying.
One brilliant, one mad.
Aye, but which is which?
Where to from here?
Antagonism to bathe.
Batheable to cholera.
Choleric to dysenteric.
Dysentery to eczema.
Eczematous to fungus.
Why not jump straight to
leprosy?
Oh, that's dropping off a lot.
You could go back to acne.
Well, there's no need to be
rash.
- Who's this?
- Murray, sir.
- Who's Murray?
- The man from the dictionary...
the one the doctor has been
working on.
Good God, well, he's had a very
busy day.
Let's keep it short, shall we?
Yes, sir.
Mr. Muncie? Accord Dr. Murray
full visitation privileges.
Let me know when they're
gonna happen.
- Yes, sir.
- Thank you.
Let's document all their
meetings, keep full details.
One could dare say it's
beautiful here.
Listen to the leaves scratch
the air.
Sometimes it sounds like
gunfire. Sometimes like...
- Like applause.
- Yes, applause.
Mr. Murray?
- Aye. I should be off then.
- Check your posts.
I will garner my thoughts and
spark them off of yours.
As iron sharpens iron...
so one man sharpens the
countenance of a friend.
Scripture. You're a man of God,
I should not be surprised.
It is by His grace alone.
I wish I had experienced
that more often.
You will, my friend.
Goodness and mercy shall follow
me all the days of my life.
Yeah, though I walk through the
valley of the shadow of death.
You're not alone, good doctor.
We are linked now...
consanguineous.
Brothers.
I looked for you this morning...
I wanted to share some good news
with you.
What news?
A new volunteer, a miracle...
he's pulling us out of the mire.
We've doubled our progress
with him already.
That's wonderful, James.
Who is he?
A friend.
A letter from our
superintendent, sir.
Oh, thank you.
Henry, could you keep an eye
for all future letters...
from the good doctor?
He is rather a private man and I
would wish to honor that.
I brought another book for you.
I see that. What is it?
One from the list Mr. Muncie
gave me.
I asked, it's one of the ones
you wanted.
You read.
I will guess which one it is,
a paragraph, a sentence.
I'm sorry, doctor.
Mrs. Merrett, Mrs. Merrett...
Mrs. Merrett, please,
what did I do?
You cannot read.
Forgive me, I should not have
presumed.
I do not need you to bring me
books, Mrs. Merrett...
it is your visits...
Please, doctor, let me be.
I can teach you.
I am what I am.
Oh, please, let me teach you.
You can teach your children.
It's freedom, Mrs. Merrett.
I can fly out of this place
on the backs of books.
I've gone to the end of the
world on the wings of words.
I can not.
When I read, no one is after me.
When I read, I am the one who is
chasing, chasing after God.
Please, I beg you... join the
chase.
Kumquat.
Oblong.
Pert.
Prunes.
Coconuts.
Chitty.
My win, Murray.
- What on earth is chitty?
- Long form of chit.
Of course, chit. Letter or note,
Indian origin, no?
That's right.
Who is she?
The impossible.
The more impossible, the greater
the love.
Do you truly believe that?
My heart is so sick.
What I know of love, the
sickness often becomes the cure.
She is my friend, she is my
dear friend...
she has suffered a terrible
loss.
Perhaps God's grace will come to
her through your love, William.
Eats, so you don't really say
the "A"?
Eats.
Wa... ush... brush and fish.
- Yes.
- Wash.
You're learning very, very fast.
The brain is wider than the sky,
for put them side by side...
the one the other will include,
with ease and you beside.
The brain is just the weight
of God, for, heft them...
pound for pound, and they will
differ if they do...
as syllable from the sound.
Did they cut the rest of the
hair on that girl off?
Mrs. Merrett?
He's making the most tremendous
progress.
Mrs. Merrett.
I'm beginning to believe the
more he's exposed...
to the world beyond these walls,
the speedier will be his cure.
You think he can be cured,
doctor?
I have to... there must be hope
for all of us.
Even the most broken of souls.
I, uh... think on it.
MURRAY My Dear Friend,
I have recommended...
to the Delegates that your name
be acknowledged...
in the First Volume of the
"New English Dictionary...
on Historical Principles", to
which your vibrant mind...
has so critically given the
breath of life.
The last fascicle is already
complete.
Expectantly, James.
Congratulations, Dr. Murray.
For giving us A to byzen.
And for the rest to come,
beginning with cab.
Thank you, sir.
It's not selling.
4,000 orders the Empire through
and he won't go any quicker.
We're the laughing stock
of all academia.
I wonder if it's time to ease
our gentle Scotsman...
off his little perch.
Stop it!
It'll be alright, they're good
kids.
We don't have to do it,
if you don't want to.
Look at me... William.
It'll be alright.
Children, I would like you
to meet a friend...
his name is William.
You must be Olive, is that
right?
Yes.
- Iris.
- Mm-hm.
Jack, and Peggy.
You must be Peter, it's good
to meet you, Peter.
And are you Clare, then?
Clare.
Truly I'm honored to meet you,
Clare!
Mr. Muncie. Watch them for me,
just for a moment.
Mm-hm.
Doctor! Wait! Wait! I'm sorry.
I never wanted that to happen.
I'm so sorry.
I remember being safe and still
I remember knowing who I was...
and I woke up and it had all
gone away, and I hated you...
so much, for so long, but now
I know you, I know who you are.
And I know the same has been
done to you.
I wrote you something.
"I can"...
"I can... because of you."
I miss my husband.
I came here that first day
to hate you.
To take your money, watch you
locked away, see you done.
You should still hate me.
Not any more.
Look what you've done!
Not that many this time, sir.
I wrote you something.
No, read it when I've gone.
I'm sorry, Eliza.
But what if I'm not?
I have killed him again.
It's all your fault.
I've killed him again
in your heart!
Mr. Coleman!
You might alert the clinic.
I have injured myself.
MINOR "My Friend, I no
longer find I have the place...
for this, I thought you might
accept it.
Remember me by it.
As a testament to our
friendship and to that...
which we created together, in
the brief and fleeting time...
Dr. Murray, Richard Brayn,
Superintendent.
Pleased to meet you, sir.
I am very proud of the
contributions that Dr. Minor...
has made, of course.
The illness has entered a new
phase. You may be shocked.
I should warn you, too, that he
may display some hostility.
You came.
Of course, I came.
I knew that you would.
Your God is very demanding.
A sacrifice was required.
I received your letter.
His love... his wife...
I stole her from the dead.
Have you gotten to the "I's"
by now?
I had some to add to your words.
But I can't seem to...
I can't seem to find my pens.
Our words, William, our words.
Perhaps that is true, perhaps...
madness... gave us words.
But you have made them yours,
they bear your secret signature.
Why did you come here?
Did you bring others?
I am alone, William.
I have reason to believe that
they are hiding...
between the spaces in the floor,
biding their time.
I'm sorry, James. I'm sorry.
For a moment, I...
dared to hope.
Your words, her... forgiveness.
It's more than forgiveness.
She... she gave me this.
Read it later, if you truly want
to know why.
Know what?
A quote, Austin, 1832.
I sent it in, but only hoping,
I wasn't sure, until now.
I can't... I can't remember
the quote.
Look it up! Look it up!
You have seen me now
and we're done.
You can leave the lunatic
to his delusions.
I came here to see my friend.
I am no man's friend,
I am a murderer.
Everything else is make believe.
So leave, leave, leave, leave,
leave, leave, leave...
leave, leave, leave, leave,
leave, leave!
And do not come back! I do not
want to see you!
Please, doctor, if your claim
that you are my friend...
is true, you will respect
that one simple wish!
Yeah.
I think no more visitors
for Dr. Minor.
Bondmade, missing from Volume
One.
A perfectly solid, everyday
English word...
and we don't have it.
I don't know how that could
have happened...
I checked the proofs for it
myself.
The University of Vienna picked
up on it.
Calm down, Philip.
We'll catch it, we'll form
an addendum.
I've been meaning to discuss
that with all of you.
Are you intending to drop
others?
The makers of this grand folly
also deign it beneath them...
to include the nouns and
adjectives denoting countries.
Hence no mention of African,
Arabian, American and so on.
In the blasted Figaro!
In the same breath, expounding
the virtues...
of their competing dictionaries.
In France, Germany, the
Netherlands.
This is a war about the spread
of colonial language...
not one with bullets and
bayonets...
but with influence and
appearance.
This is utterly absurd.
a superabundance of redundancy,
Dr. Murray.
We need your focus.
The language is escaping you,
you are losing.
What precisely are you saying,
Mr. Gell?
This is Oxford. We do not lose.
Clearly the only course
remaining...
Bondmade.
What was that? Speak up,
Freddie.
Bondmade. I borrowed the proof
from the scriptorium...
to use in one of my lectures.
I forgot to replace it. I am
responsible for its exclusion.
It doesn't change a thing.
Also the absence of African,
Arabian, and American.
I convinced James not to include
them.
So you see, gentlemen, you are
inculpating the wrong man.
You're right, Philip, there is
only one course of action.
I will resign my post from
the board of delegates.
We shall make an announcement
on it.
And the project will go on,
with James.
I really don't see how...
Philip, please!
Have it in writing to the Press
offices in the morning.
He's lying through his teeth.
Of course he is.
Then why let them get away
with it?
Didn't you see? Dr. Murray is a
breath away from shattering.
And without Furnivall's
meddling...
all we need do is wait.
Have a quiet word with Bradley,
I suspect he is just...
the ticket for a more malleable
pair of hands at the helm.
James... what's the matter?
I'm adrift, Ada. The day has
been one of loss.
I need to tell you some things.
Don't go on... what you've
done...
there is nothing you can tell me
to make this right!
All the wisdom, all the
diligence and you simply...
How long have you known about
his madness?
How much time have you spent
with this man?
Why are you so angry? What
difference can it possibly make?
His work on the dictionary
proves he is sane.
He fooled that jury and he
fooled you.
What about repentance, Ada?
What about redemption?
we all deserve more than
to have it all...
Stop!
I could call into question
the morality...
of every invisible volunteer
we've ever leaned on.
This one hits his children,
that one's on the whiskey...
this one, didn't you hear, he
cheats on the Times crossword.
Remove the blaggard
from the list.
He is a murderer! He lied
to you.
Have you never lied?
Have you not?
What are you so afraid of, that
a bad man can be redeemed?
Isn't that what we believe, what
we whisper to our children...
at night, what we pray for?
Forgiveness.
I don't know who you're
preaching to.
Neither do I.
"Thus they in lowliest plight
repentant stood praying...
from the mercy seat above,
prevenient grace descending...
had removed the stony from their
hearts and made new flesh".
Milton, Paradise Lost,
prevenient grace, Ada.
From before the fall,
salvation for all...
if we choose to engage it.
"If love... then what?"
What is that?
A note, from the widow, asking
the question of the killer.
"Assythment - satisfaction
for an injury done.
Compensation, reparation,
indemnification.
have still the right
for assythment."
I don't understand.
It means to pay everything back.
The guilty make recompense
the victim.
I thought he'd already given
her money.
No, Ada, his life, with his
life.
"If love... then what?"
Is what she wrote to him.
And his response.
What are you going to do?
What can I do?
Sometimes when we push away...
that is when we most need
to be resisted.
♪ When I am dead my dearest ♪
Please, let me in, let me in!
I need to see him, let me in!
Mr. Muncie, please, I know you
can hear me, let me in!
I need to see him!
Let me in!
- Mrs. Merrett...
- I need to see him, please.
It is best you went away now
and you not come back.
Please, I need to see him.
Mrs. Merrett, I'm sorry.
Oh, I need to see him, please!
No!
I need to see him! Please!
♪ When showers and dewdrops
hurt ♪
♪ And if thou wilt remember ♪
♪ And if I wilt forget ♪
BRAYN It is time to
commence a course...
of more invasive and more
experimental treatments...
all procedures will be fully
documented.
William... are we ready?
Most rightfully so.
Thank you, doctor.
Secure his arms, all right,
here we go.
That's it. Steady. Good boy.
Come on, let's get him over.
Up you go. All right.
- Doctor, please bear with me.
- Yes.
All right, that's it, that's it.
Steady.
Again.
- Same again, sir.
- Oh, no.
Again.
Oh, yeah, we've got you.
- One more, sir, good boy.
- I asked first.
Up now, up now. Steady.
Once more.
- You've got them?
- Yes.
Mrs. Murray.
My name is Church, I'm with the
South London Chronicle.
May I speak with your husband,
ma'am?
The story runs
tomorrow, sir, everything...
you, the big book, the widow
Merrett.
There's nothing I can do
about it now.
I just wanted to give you
fair warning.
But these... I haven't given'em
to the paper.
I thought, maybe, you should
hold on to them.
It looks like he's in a bad way,
sir.
Mother!
No, no... go upstairs and play up
there.
James.
If I may say, sir, between you
and me, I've been concerned...
about some of Dr. Brayn's
medical techniques.
We had to take precautions.
William? It's James, William.
William.
It's no use, I'm afraid.
He's not here.
I don't know where he is,
but he's not here.
Wait for me outside.
Dr. Murray, I must ask that you
inform me...
before you pay a visit.
I came as soon as I knew.
Yes, but it's not a club, sir,
this is a medical facility.
Dr. Minor is a patient
in my care.
He is my friend, my brother.
Yes, he's my friend, as well.
And he's one of the bravest men
I have ever known.
However, this is severe
catalepsy.
It's a fair question...
whether or not the soul has
already left the vessel.
"Divided from himself and his
fair judgment...
without which we are pictures
or mere beasts."
How could this have happened?
I must ask you to leave
immediately.
No, he doesn't belong here,
not like this.
On the contrary, he does not
belong anywhere else.
Please allow us to get on
with our work.
We have a great deal to do.
It's alright, William.
Please! It's alright, William...
it's alright, William,
it's all right.
The last 400 years have been
defined by his quotes alone.
We were at our darkest moment.
He gave us life.
I'm asking for your help here,
Ben.
To tell the truth of what
he's done.
Let it be known, not this.
My only regret is that you did
not come forward...
with this much sooner.
What there is to be known has
already been said... right here.
Written. Didn't you see?
But this is the life of a man.
All that he is will end with him
in that place.
And he is where he should be.
What use an act
of pointless charity?
Then I resign.
There will be no need for such
theatrics.
William Minor will be struck
from all acknowledgments.
You are to be welcomed, for as
long as you like...
as a contributor to the
dictionary.
The editorship will pass
immediately to Bradley.
I will be proposing this at
an emergency meeting...
of the delegates this afternoon.
I do not expect any dissent.
I won't thieve any more
of your time.
Nor I yours.
Yes, sir?
Is the master of the house in?
James... is everything alright?
I'm sorry, Freddie, I didn't
know where else to go.
I've lost everything.
Everything is broken.
I wanted to document the history
of each and every thing.
To offer the world a book that
gives the meaning...
of everything in God's creation.
Or at least the English part of
it, but it has defeated me.
And now I've paid for it
with everything...
that ever meant anything to me.
You know, there is another book
that purports to do just that.
But it has already beaten you
to the punch.
Come with me. Come, I want to
show you something.
I need me dunnage.
What, with a sprat?
How'd you do that?
Dunnage? Sprat? Blag?
How many new words to replace
the old?
How many new words for things
that have yet to be imagined?
How many of them in your all
encompassing book?
No language can ever be
permanently the same, James.
Not if it springs forth
from life.
But how can the work be ended
if not ever completed?
You have given us its heart
along with a great jolt...
to begin the first few beats.
Generations after you will
continue this work...
because you have showed them
the way.
But it will never be completed.
Let it go.
Tend to yourself, leave the
project to me.
I have a few tricks for Jowett
and his lackey Gell...
that they have not considered
in their maneuvering.
Ada?
With Bradley in charge and the
University press...
firmly driving the endeavour,
we believe we can keep...
to our desired target of 704
pages a year...
doubling current sales
estimates.
Thank you, Mr. Gell.
Well, gentlemen, I believe we
are all now...
sufficiently informed to put
the motion to a vote.
I'm sorry my husband is unable
to attend.
I would like to ask permission
to say a few words in his stead.
Mrs. Murray, this is a closed
meeting.
I'm afraid you will have
to leave.
My family and I have given much
for the glory of the delegates..
Mr. Gell, I am certain they can
give a few moments...
of their time in return.
Of course, Mrs. Murray.
We are here to listen,
please, go ahead.
My husband has this silly,
little leather parchment.
On it, he's engraved a creed.
"Only a most diligent life."
Diligence. I looked it up,
in your dictionary.
Constant and earnest effort to
accomplish what is undertaken.
Persistence, application,
but also, toil, and pain.
Some of you think my husband
a fool.
Obstinate. Naive.
Driven to what he is by fear...
of what awaits us all on the
other side, but he isn't.
He sees the world, all of it,
with its myriad choices...
and he chooses to be what he is.
Yet, two such men found each
other in our time.
My husband and his friend, the
murderous madman.
Together they have given us
something extraordinary.
I am here to ask you to take
exception...
to our prevailing natures.
I'm here to ask you not to
punish them for it.
Bradley told me you quit.
I did what I could in there,
but they're a tough lot.
We're leaving this place.
We're going back to London.
The book, it is not just
yours to quit.
It is ours, remember? Mine, the
children's, countless others'.
And they can, James, if there
is love.
I know the answer now.
I know the answer to the widow's
question.
I want you to do something
for me.
I will.
I want you to go to her and look
her in the eyes.
And if you see forgiveness,
if you see love...
I want you to help your friend.
Yeah.
- Here, my man.
- Thank you, sir.
He gave me that the last time
I saw him.
The last time he was lucid.
They won't let me see him.
Can you make them let me in?
It's no use. He's not the same
as you remember.
If I've forgiven him, why should
they go on punishing him?
Thank you for seeing me...
at such short notice, Sir
Charles.
Freddie is an old friend.
I have to warn you though,
Mr. Murray...
the American murderer
is a scar...
perhaps one that is still
too fresh.
Perhaps this will heal it.
Hardly so.
Any politician espousing his
cause is certain...
to face public outrage, chances
of a pardon...
or a reprieve, are virtually
non-existent.
What price justice? What price
mercy?
Expensive to your first, cheap
but unpopular to your second.
Look here, levers can be pulled,
get you a hearing.
But if I were you, I would do
all I can to find out...
who will be called to it,
and I would stack the deck.
William? William, can you hear
me?
- Everybody out.
- It's James.
Everybody out.
William, you need to hear us.
Can you hear me?
I brought Mrs. Merrett to see
you.
Leave him be!
- She needs to talk, you need to...
- Leave him be!
With all due respect, sir,
leave them be!
William? William?
William, I'm here.
It's Eliza.
Do you remember, William?
"If love... then what?"
If love... then what, William?
If love... then love.
If love, then love.
Please stand.
Do you know why you are here,
Dr. Minor?
I do.
And in your opinion, Sergeant,
have the circumstances changed?
No, sir.
Under what conditions did he
enter catalepsy?
Documented procedures of
treatment.
With the patient's agreement?
Of course. Gentlemen, with
respect, the matter here...
begs a different question.
Where and into which hands would
misguided compassion...
release him, there is nowhere
else. This is his home.
Thank you, Mrs. Merrett.
Is there anything further you
would like to say?
Yes, I would.
My husband didn't deserve what
happened to him.
He worked hard. Kept his family
together.
Then one day he was gone, and
nothing could bring him back.
What happened to him isn't fair.
For a long time after he was
gone...
I didn't want to remember him,
not even what he looked like.
I want to say I'm sorry
about that.
He deserved more than that.
My husband was a sweet man, but
he could get angry, too.
Once he got so cross, he kicked
the heater...
'cause it weren't working,
he put his foot right through...
burnt it on the hot coals, he
was limping for weeks after.
One day he caught Jack behind
him, hopping along...
all hobbled and all, like him,
do you remember?
He looked at Jack, and he
started to laugh.
He laughed so hard hobbling,
he nearly fell over.
I think that's why he was often
so cross.
It's cause he wanted his babies,
you were all his babies...
he wanted them to make him
laugh.
I think if George was here now,
he'd think all this is unfair.
I think this would make him
angry.
He wouldn't have a lot of fancy
words to say about it.
But I know he would want it
to stop.
Sir, please, a moment of your
time.
I will deliver my report in two
days. You will know then.
We are not asking for your
full deliberation.
Just a hint at which way you
lean.
Release will be denied.
The particulars of his
treatment...
that have come to light are
troubling...
Is that not enough to...
But they are an indictment of
the entire criminally insane...
system of which this board is
not a competent judge.
Dr. Minor is a severely
disturbed man.
For his own safety, the
recommendation...
cannot be given to release him
into the open.
Sir, is there no other way?
Whatever you intend to do,
Dr. Murray, you have one day.
Then I have to submit my report.
We can try one last measure,
James.
But you had better be prepared
to lay it all on.
Your timing couldn't be worse.
An armed gang of Latvians have
holed up...
in a building on Sidney Street.
The Scots Guards have it
surrounded...
and the whole thing has
escalated into a siege.
A bloody disaster, and it's put
him in a foul mood.
Wait here.
I'm sorry, chaps, no go,
bad timing.
Sir? Sir? Mr. Churchill, please!
Forgive me, that was insolent.
I don't know you, sir. I don't
know the sort of man you are.
But the office you occupy
permits me to have desires...
as to the kind of man I would
want you to be.
Your decisions affect all the
lives of this land.
And I am here, standing before
you, for a single one.
A complicated, pained and soured
one, but a life nonetheless.
And therefore deserving and
worthy and precious.
If you believe, as I would have
you believe...
that every individual life
deserves its own chance...
please, hear what I have come
to say.
Please, sir? All right.
I suppose I did say
lay it all on.
Charles?
I will not release Dr. Minor.
The prime minister won't
countenance it.
The public won't stand for it.
Fortunately your lexicon
provides us with the means...
to conceal the unpalatable.
What I will do is deport
Dr. Minor.
I gather he has family
in Connecticut.
He does, sir.
I shall let the board know,
should he be released...
he is to be sent home.
Undesirable alien... let America
manage her errant son.
Settle this matter, Dr. Murray.
Go back to your work.
The nation has need of you, and
allow me to get back to mine.
Thank you, sir.
- Congratulations, doctor.
- Thank you, thank you.
May I introduce you to Freddie
Furnivall.
- It is an honor, doctor.
- That is impossible.
They're ready, sir.
Ah, wait a moment, please.
Yes, sir.
I'll be right here, William,
right over there. All right?
That's good, and
if you can hold on three...
one, two, three.
This is ours. Something to read
on the ship.
Does she know?
She does.
Tell her I... you'll tell her
then.
I will.
Have you seen the latest proof
of the front cover?
You see, the fortunate thing
about these awful people...
is they believe in the divine
right of rule of the monarch.
Their system falls to pieces if
they don't abide...
by its silly intricacies.
So, we use it against them.
Your book is safe, James.
You are safe at its helm for as
long as you wish...
or until you shuffle off this
mortal coil.
- Yes.
- What now?
Now and forever beyond, my dear
Gell...
Dr. Murray is the dictionary.
Perhaps you should consider
taking a rest.
I hear the South of France
is quite the place...
for recharging one's spirits.